John A. Casazza Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Course Materials, 1984-2004 (Box 26-33)
  - Restructuring and Its Impact on the Cost and Reliability of Electric Power Systems, 2001 (Box 32)
  - Take My Grid...Please!: Blackouts and How to Prevent Them, 2003, (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Transmission and Ancillary Services: Cost Identification and Tariff Development, binder, 1996, (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Transmission, Competition, Coordination, and Contracts in the 1990s, binder, 1992, (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Transmission, Competition, Coordination, and Contracts in the 1990s, binder, 1992 (Box 33)
  - Transmission Systems: How They Really Work, binder, 1991, (3 folders) (Box 33)
- Miscellany, 1938-2018 (Box 33-35)
  The Miscellany series includes correspondence, photographs, and other miscellaneous material pertaining to Casazza’s life and career. Much of the correspondence is related to Casazza’s interest in improving the technical competence of government officials and his concerns about the future of the engineering profession. Congratulatory letters on various professional accomplishments and a small amount of personal correspondence are also included. The photographs and clippings primarily document Casazza’s projects in the electric power industry. Also present are several portraits of Casazza.
  Material types include correspondence, photographs, clippings, notes, a family history of the Casazza and Russo families, an oral history interview, copies of a patent, and résumés and other biographical material.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Awards, 1974-1978, 1989-1996 (Box 33)
  - Biographical material, 1953-2016, (2 folders) (Box 33)
  - Correspondence, 1969-2018 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence, 1969-2018, (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Family history, 1966, 1974, 1996-1997, 2006-2008 (Box 34)
  - Notes, 1938-1945 (Box 34)
  - Oral history interview with IEEE History Center, 1994 (Box 34)
  - Patent for power injector control means for transmission networks, 1974-1976 (Box 34)
  - Photographs, 1946-2003, (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Photographs, 1946-2003 (Box 35)
  - Press clippings and publicity photographs, binder, 1949-1951, 1964-2004, (3 folders) (Box 35)
- Digital File, 2000-2012 (DF)
  The Digital File series contains the contents of floppy disks and CDs created and used by Casazza and overlaps with material from the other series. The series documents his professional activities with Power Engineers Supporting Truth, the American Education Insitute, and the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers. Also included are copies of various book drafts, speeches and slide presentations, articles, and reports written by Casazza. Major topics include electric power failures (especially the Northeast blackout of 2003), electric power deregulation, and labor and personnel issues affecting the electrical engineering profession.
  Material types include correspondence, meeting minutes, PowerPoint presentations, book drafts, articles, and reports.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material. The file structure of the digital content has been maintained as received.
  - American Education Institute, 2002-2006, mss86357_222_083; mss86357_222_105; mss86357_222_122; mss86357_222_128; mss86357_222_130; mss86357_222_131 (DF)
  - Biographical material, 2003-2004, mss86357_222_100
  - Cooper Union alumni images, 2010, mss86357_222_150
  - Correspondence
    - 2001-2002, mss86357_222_102
    - 2002, mss86357_222_078
    - 2003, mss86357_222_010; mss86357_222_092
    - 2003-2006, mss86357_222_129
    - 2004, mss86357_222_016; mss86357_222_060; mss86357_222_093; mss86357_222_094
    - 2005, mss86357_222_055; mss86357_222_056
    - 2005-2006, mss86357_222_095
    - 2005-2007, mss86357_222_054
    - 2006, mss86357_222_096
    - 2007, mss86357_222_148; mss86357_222_149
    - 2008, mss86357_222_119; mss86357_222_127
  - Course materials
    - Distributed/Dispersed Generation, 2001, mss86357_222_051
    - El Salvador courses, 2004, mss86357_222_085; mss86357_222_086; mss86357_222_087; mss86357_222_088; mss86357_222_089; mss86357_222_090; mss86357_222_091
    - Electric System Security, 2002, mss86357_222_005; mss86357_222_007
    - Future Electric Transmission Systems, 2002, mss86357_222_005; mss86357_222_006; mss86357_222_007; mss86357_222_110; mss86357_222_112; mss86357_222_113
    - How to Run a Profitable Continuing Education Program, 2005, mss86357_222_095
    - Take My Grid...Please!: Blackouts and How to Prevent Them, 2003, mss86357_222_008
  - Electric power deregulation, 2001-2007, mss86357_222_011; mss86357_222_037; mss86357_222_038; mss86357_222_074; mss86357_222_075; mss86357_222_099; mss86357_222_147
  - Electric power failures, 2002-2005, mss86357_222_020; mss86357_222_021; mss86357_222_022; mss86357_222_059; mss86357_222_070; mss86357_222_071; mss86357_222_072; mss86357_222_073; mss86357_222_146; mss86357_222_149; mss86357_222_165
  - Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, 2000-2007, mss86357_222_049; mss86357_222_077; mss86357_222_078; mss86357_222_079; mss86357_222_092; mss86357_222_098; mss86357_222_106; mss86357_222_132; mss86357_222_134; mss86357_222_136; mss86357_222_137; mss86357_222_148
  - Labor and personnel issues, 2002-2007, mss86357_222_011; mss86357_222_024; mss86357_222_025; mss86357_222_039; mss86357_222_146; mss86357_222_149
  - National power surveys, 2003-2004, mss86357_222_066; mss86357_222_071; mss86357_222_146
  - Power Engineers Supporting Truth, 2003-2010, mss86357_222_012; mss86357_222_014; mss86357_222_021; mss86357_222_061; mss86357_222_062; mss86357_222_063; mss86357_222_064; mss86357_222_065; mss86357_222_066; mss86357_222_067; mss86357_222_068; mss86357_222_069; mss86357_222_074
  - Speeches and writings
    - Articles
      - "Aging Transformers Risk More Blackouts," 2004, mss86357_222_017
      - "Blackout Again," 2005, mss86357_222_018
      - "Capacity and Energy Requirements," 2008, mss86357_222_081
      - "Criteria for Investing in the Transmission System from the Consumer Viewpoint," 2004, mss86357_222_023
      - "Electric Power Deregulation-Bad Idea?" 2005, mss86357_222_108
      - "Electric Power, National Security, and Our Economic Welfare," 2003, mss86357_222_052
      - "Electric Power System Reliability and its Uncertainties," 2004, mss86357_222_029
      - "Electric Power Technology for the Future: A Way to Proceed," 2008, mss86357_222_119
      - "Electric Power Transmission Systems," 2006, mss86357_222_138
      - "Electrons vs. People," 2006, mss86357_222_048
      - "Errant Economics? Lousy Law? Market Manipulation? All Three!," 2001, mss86357_222_076
      - "Financial Markets and the Role in the Electric Power Industry," 2008, mss86357_222_082
    - Books
      - The Development of Electric Power Transmission: The Role Played by Technology, Institutions, and People, 2003-2004, mss86357_222_142; mss86357_222_143
      - Forgotten Roots: Electric Power, Profits, Democracy and a Profession, 2007-2008, mss86357_222_001; mss86357_222_002; mss86357_222_003; mss86357_222_004; mss86357_222_010; mss86357_222_011; mss86357_222_012; mss86357_222_103; mss86357_222_151
      - Sham? Shame!: Inside the Electric Power Industry, 2001-2003, mss86357_222_104; mss86357_222_139; mss86357_222_140; mss86357_222_141
      - Superpower: A Historical Novel About the People Responsible for our National Power Grid, 2012, mss86357_222_014; mss86357_222_161
      - Understanding Electric Power Systems, 2002-2008, mss86357_222_114; mss86357_222_115; mss86357_222_116; mss86357_222_117; mss86357_222_118; mss86357_222_120; mss86357_222_121; mss86357_222_123; mss86357_222_124; mss86357_222_125; mss86357_222_126; mss86357_222_145
    - Reports
      - "CIGRE Glossary of Terms Used in the Electricity Supply Industry," 2001, mss86357_222_097
      - "Comments on the Dussan Report Proposals for Changes in Electric Power Policies in El Salvador, " 2004, mss86357_222_147
      - "Government, Engineers, Politics and the Final Report on the August 14, 2003 Blackout," 2004, mss86357_222_017
      - "Pakistan's Electric System," 2004, mss86357_222_047
      - "Report on the Events of September 28th, 2003 Culminating in the Separation of the Italian Power System from the other UCTE Networks," 2004, mss86357_222_109
    - Speeches and presentations
      - "Building a Power Grid in Developing Countries," 2003, mss86357_222_034
      - "Competition and Reliability in North American Electricity Markets," 2005, mss86357_222_057; mss86357_222_058
      - "Effect of Future Technical and Regulatory Developments on Transmission System," 2006, mss86357_222_040; mss86357_222_042
      - "Electric Power Systems," 2005, mss86357_222_027
      - "Electric Utility Deregulation and its Implications," 2001, mss86357_222_037
      - "End of an Era: History of Electric Power Transmission," 2005, mss86357_222_027
      - "How to Have a Good National Energy Policy," 2004, mss86357_222_045
      - "Impact of Electric Power Restructuring: A U.S.A. Overview," 2001, mss86357_222_050
      - "Impact of Power Industry Restructuring on Power System Planning, Operation, and Economics," 2004, mss86357_222_033
      - "Impact of the Decline of Engineering Influence in Electric Power Decisions," 2004-2005, mss86357_222_030; mss86357_222_038; mss86357_222_133
      - "Inside the Electric Power Industry: Past, Present, Future," 2004, 2001; mss86357_222_036
      - Lists of talks, 2006-2007, mss86357_222_026; mss86357_222_147
      - Nigeria blackout talk, 2002, mss86357_222_165
      - "Shortages of Electric Power Industry Personnel in the U.S.," 2006, mss86357_222_039
      - "Small Consumers," 2001, mss86357_222_036
      - Testimonies before federal agencies, 2004-2007, mss86357_222_107
      - "Transmission Choices for the Future," 2002, mss86357_222_035
      - "Transmission Regulatory Issues in the United States," 2004, mss86357_222_030; mss86357_222_031